VINCENT J. SCHAEFER PAPERS (UA902.010) 1891-1993
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives
- Biographical & Autobiographical Materials, 1909-1993; Undated; 12; 13.5
  - Personal Records, 1922-1993; Undated; 12.1
    - Whiteface Mountain-Negatives and Photos, Undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Whiteface Mountain Research-Maps, Pamphlets, Postcards, Undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Whitney, Willis- Mysterious Bug and Tree in Nassau, Bahamas- Other Correspondence Included, 1941; 1954; Undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Winter Sports in Schenectady, 1957; Undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Woestyne South (Schaefer Home), 1942 September 27 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Worlds Fair-Photos, 1945 February 16 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Writings by Others on Serendipity and Related Topics, 1989 December 04; Fall 1991; 1992 August 07 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - York University Honorary Degree, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Dutch Barns, 1930-1993; Undated; 12.2
    This subseries documents Vincent Schaefer’s interests in the construction, history and preservation of Dutch barns. Although the majority of the records are from Schaefer’s retirement during the late 1980s and early 1990s when he had significant time to devote to this pursuit, researching and surveying Dutch barns was a lifelong hobby. For example, there are images of barns from the 1930s and a newspaper clipping discussing a planned lecture by Schaefer on Dutch barns from January 1939. Schaefer was very active in the Dutch Barn Preservation Society and received a Preservation League of New York State Award in 1991 for restoration and protection of the Greater Wemp Barn. This multi-year effort to save and ultimately relocate the Greater Wemp Barn is well-documented in this subseries. Other materials of interest are several volumes of Dutch Barn Research Miscellany, a publication edited by Schaefer, articles on barns written by Schaefer, background information on barns in New York compiled by Schaefer, especially those in the Capital District, and numerous slides and photographs.
    - "An Analysis of the Roof Line Evolution of the New World Dutch Barn"- Vincent Schaefer, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Anchor Beams, Undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Annotated and Hand Drawn Maps, 1988; Undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Background Information, Illustrations and Glossary of Dutch Barns, Undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - "Barn Preservation Through Easements Feasibility Study"- William Engleman, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Bogart/Northrup Dutch Barn, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Bull and Wells Homestead, 1991; Undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Clippings and News Releases, 1939-1992; Undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Completed Dutch Barn Measurement Forms- Questions and Survey Notes, 1997-1998 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1942; 1971-1973; 1987-1990 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1991-1992; Undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - "Development Patterns of Farms on the Great Flats-Schenectady"- Vincent Schaefer, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Dutch Barn Book Discards, Undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Dutch Barn Illustrations, 1992-1993; Undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Dutch Barn Pictures, 1930-1934; 1937; Undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Dutch Barn Pictures- Negatives, 1964; 1976; Undated (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Dutch Barn Photographs- Photographs, 1963-1991; Undated (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Dutch Barn Pictures- Slides, 1954-1990; Undated (Box 9, Folder 18-19)
    - The Dutch Barn Preservation Society, 1989-1993; Undated (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Dutch Barn Preservation Society- Board of Trustees Meetings, 1987-1989; Undated (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Dutch Barn Preservation Newsletter, 1988-1992 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Dutch Barn Research Journal, 1991-1992 (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Dutch Barn Research Miscellany, 1989-1991 (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Dutch Barn Research Miscellany- Edited by Vincent J Schaefer, Vol. 1, No. 1-3, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Dutch Barn Research Miscellany- Edited by Vincent J Schaefer, Vol.2, No. 1-2, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Dutch Barn Research Miscellany- Edited by Vincent J Schaefer, Vol.3, No. 1-2, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Dutch Barn Research Miscellany- Edited by Vincent J Schaefer, Vol.4, No.1, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Dutch Barns Found in the Townships of St. Johnsville and Palatine Montgomery County, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - Dutch Barns in New Jersey, 1988-1990; Undated (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - "The Dutch Barns of America"- Vincent J Schaefer, Undated (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - "The Dutch Barns of Eastern New York, 1680-1990"- Vincent J. Schaefer, Undated (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - Dutch Barns of New York Manuscript, Undated (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - "The Dutch Barns of the Mohawk Valley"- Vincent Schaefer, Undated (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - Field Trip Notes, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 35)
    - Five Rivers Rambles, "The Dutch Barns of the Five Rivers Area", Undated (Box 9, Folder 36)
    - Hallenback/Crouse Barn, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 37)
    - Hay Barrack Structures, 1989; Undated (Box 9, Folder 38)
    - Herrington Farms Dutch Barn, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 39)
    - Johannes Lawyer Barn, Undated (Box 9, Folder 40)
    - Mabie New Dutch Barns, 1977; 1992-1993; Undated (Box 9, Folder 41)
    - National Trust for Historic Preservation- Honor Awards Program Nomination for Carl Touhey, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 42)
    - Notes on Early Settlers and Genealogical History, Undated (Box 9, Folder 43)
    - Preservation League of New York State Award for Vincent Schaefer, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 44)
    - Preservation League of New York State Nomination for Carl Touhey, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Rensselaer Institute Dutch Barn Data Copies, 1985-1986; 1988; Undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Rensselaer County Survey-Schenectady County Survey-Dutch Barns, 1987-1992 (Box 10, Folder 3-4)
    - The Reporter: News of the Dutch Barn Preservation Society, 1990-1992 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Schenectady County Historical Society, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Status Lists of Dutch Barns, Undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Teller/Schermerhorn Dutch Barn, 1988; Undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Van Bergen Dutch Barn, Undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Wemp Barn at Schoharie Crossing Historic Site, 1988-1989; Undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Wemp Barn- Relocated to Carl Touhey's Onesquethaw Creek Estate, 1990; Undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - The Wemple/Dellamont Dutch Barn, Undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - "What is a Dutch Barn? An Opinion"- Vincent Schaefer, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Written Analysis- Photos and Maps of Dutch Barns in New York, Undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Local History and Archeology, 1909-1993; Undated; 12.3
    This subseries features materials related to history in New York, especially near the Capital District, and archeological research, two of Vincent Schaefer’s important personal interests. Schaefer was a vice president and trustee of the Schenectady County Historical Society and wrote for the organization’s Milestone newsletter. He also helped found the Van Epps-Hartley chapter of the New York State Archeological Association, which was formally organized in 1931, and later served as chapter president. There is significant correspondence about the chapter’s founding and several articles authored by Schaefer about archeological sites and artifacts in this subseries. There also is correspondence between Schaefer and New York State Archeologist Arthur C. Parker, then museum director at the City of Rochester, New York’s Municipal Museum.
    - Adirondack History, 1986; 1989; 1992; Undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Albany County History, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - "A Little of the Story and Interests as Told by Old Military Buttons"- Robert M. Hartley, 1937 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - "The Amateur in the Field of Archeology"- VJ Schaefer, 1934 March 30 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Annotated Map of Schenectady, Undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Archeological Miscellany, ca. 1993-1988 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Archeological Research-Exploration-Lone Scout Publication, 1921-1924; 1992; Undated (Box 11, Folder 7-9)
    - Archeological Sites Explored by Schaefer-Handwritten Manuscripts, Notes, Drawings, 1926-1927 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Cave Life Manuscript and Photographs, Undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Christian Wildlife Sanctuary Trail, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - City of Rochester, New York's Municipal Museum-Rochester Museum of Arts and Sciences, 1940-1943; 1945; 1947 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Eastern States Archeological Federation, 1934; 1937; 1944 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Eastern States Archeological Federation-Meetings, 1935 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Field of Archeology in New York State-Handwritten Report and Notes, Undated (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Field Studies and Notes, Undated (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Five Rivers Area, Undated (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - The Formulation of a Tree Calendar in the Mohawk Valley-Vincent Schaefer, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Fundamentals of Geology-Handwritten Notes, Undated (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - General Correspondence, 1927-1983 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - General Correspondence, 1986-1991; Undated (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - Glacial Lake Albany, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - Hand Drawn Maps and Diagrams, Undated (Box 11, Folder 24)
    - "How to be a Fossil Maker"-Vincent Schaefer, 1947 (Box 11, Folder 25)
    - Images of Archeological Objects, Undated (Box 11, Folder 26)
    - Lake Champlain Tercentenary, 1909 July 04-1909 July 10 (Box 11, Folder 27)
    - Lake George Institute of History, Art and Science, and Lake George Historical Association, 1964-1967; 1970-1976; Undated (Box 11, Folder 28-29)
    - Land Surveys, Undated (Box 11, Folder 30)
    - "Let's Find An Indian Arrowhead"-Vincent Schaefer, Undated (Box 11, Folder 31)
    - *Living History*, Undated (Box 11, Folder 32)
    - Mabie House, 1974 (Box 11, Folder 33)
    - "Mohawks in the Lower Valley"-Vincent Schaefer, 1955 (Box 11, Folder 34)
    - Mohawk Valley, 1934; 1938; 1946; 1952; Undated (Box 11, Folder 35)
    - Montgomery County, Crater of Unknown Origin, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 36)
    - Montgomery County History, Undated (Box 11, Folder 37)
    - Montgomery Manor-Montgomery County, 1992-1993; Undated (Box 11, Folder 38)
    - Negatives, Archeological and Historic Sites, 1928-1961; Undated (Box 11, Folder 39)
    - New York State Archeological Association, Including *The Bulletin* and Constitution, 1940-1987; Undated (Box 11, Folder 40-41)
    - News clips-Archeological and Historic Topics, 1933; 1936; 1979; Undated (Box 11, Folder 42)
    - News clips-Schaefer Speaking Engagements on Archeological Topics and Van Epps-Hartley Chapter Activities, 1934; 1936; 1941; 1946 (Box 11, Folder 43)
    - Owasco Aspect, Undated (Box 11, Folder 44)
    - Painting of a Native American Woman- Ralph Tillman, 1947 (Box 11, Folder 45)
    - Photo Album- Archeology and Nature Expeditions, 1920s (Oversized 10)
    - Photographs- Archeological and Historic Sites, 1936; 1952; Undated (Box 11, Folder 46)
    - Photographs- Geological Sites, Undated (Box 11, Folder 47)
    - Pottery Beach- Remnants of Old Fort Niskayuna, Undated (Box 11, Folder 48)
    - Pre-Iroquoian Occupations of New York- Mentioning Turnbull, Van Orden, Schermerhorn, Vosburg, Undated (Box 11, Folder 49)
    - Prehistoric Man in the Mohawk Region- Percy Van Epps, 1935 (Box 11, Folder 50)
    - Saratoga County History, Undated (Box 11, Folder 51)
    - Schenectady County History-Including *The Milestone* and VJ Schaefer Papers, 1909-1989; Undated (Box 11, Folder 52)
    - Schenectady Museum, 1941; 1952; 1955 (Box 11, Folder 53)
    - Schaefer- Notes on Expeditions about Archeology, Undated (Box 11, Folder 54)
    - Schoharie County History, 1941-1987; Undated (Box 11, Folder 55)
    - Slides- Archeological and Historic Sites, 1944-1988; Undated (Box 11, Folder 56)
    - Slides- New York Sites, 1964-1966; 1969; 1971; 1973 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Society for American Archeology Notebook, 1939-1942 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Survey of History and the Natural Sciences of the Five Rivers Area, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Turnbull Site, 1927; 1937; Undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - The Van-Epps Hartley Bulletin, 1936-1940 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Van Epps-Hartley Chapter-New York State Archeological Association, 1931-1959; Undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Van Epps-Hartley Chapter Receipts, 1932-1935; Undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - "Van Orden Component-Hudsonian Aspect"- Vincent J. Schaefer, Undated (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - The Vosburg Site, 1988; Undated (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Vroman's Nose- History, Undated (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Vroman's Nose Preservation Corporation, 1988-1992 (Box 12, Folder 11)